Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today is the 22nd day of the
עומר Omer and we are the official דף Daf is ס״ה Samech-Hey
65. We're behind. We pick up on the very top of ס״ד
עמוד ב׳. Samech-Daled Amud-Bet. We have actually a few lines to get
to the משנה. Mishna. We'll try to do that quickly so as
not to get too caught up in yesterday's סוגיה, Sugya, but it
was an important discussion yesterday. The משנה Mishna said
that if a man said to his wife that he has no
brothers, when on his deathbed, he says he has no brothers or
that he has sons that would get her out of יבום, Yibbum,
then he's believed. But if he says the opposite, he has brothers,
he doesn't have sons, he's not believed. So it seemed to be
that the rule was, didn't explain why, but the rule was we
believe him to free her from יבום Yibbum not to bind her
in יבום. Yibbum. The גמרא Gemara said that well, that's the position
of רבי, Rebbe, quoted a ברייתא Baraita that רבי Rebbe exactly said
that נאמן להתיר ואינו נאמן לאסור, ne'eman lehatir ve'eino ne'eman le'asor, but
it's quoted a position of רבי נתן Rebbe Natan that said he's
believed both ways. And the scenario there was that when he was
marrying her, he said the right thing, the thing that would get
her out of יבום, Yibbum, "I don't have brothers, I do have
sons," and on his deathbed he retracted it. And רבי נתן Rebbe
Natan said, "Well, then he's believed to make her forbidden. He is
believed on what he said on his deathbed." So it seems that
our משנה Mishna and רבי נתן Rebbe Natan disagreed, but the גמרא
Gemara is saying maybe there's a way they do agree. And in
its attempt to say that they do agree, it is clarifying why
to believe him or not to believe him. So let's just pick
up with that. It was let's I mean it's the last line
on ס״ד עמוד א׳. Samech-Daled Amud-Aleph. Okay, it says like this: אלא
אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, or three lines from the bottom. מתניתין,
matnitin, our משנה Mishna where he is not believed when he says
on his deathbed that he has brothers or no sons, דמוחזק לן
ולא מוחזק לן באחי ולא מוחזק לן בבני. demuchzak lan velo muchzak
lan be'achi velo muchzak lan bevanai. We assume he has no brothers
and no sons, so therefore we assume no brothers, she's not obligated
in יבום. Yibbum. דאמרינן כיון דלא מוחזק לן בבני ולא באחי, de'amrinan
keivan delo muchzak lan bevanai velo be'achi, so therefore since we assume
neither, אמר יש לי בנים נאמן. amar yesh li banim ne'eman. If
he says something that reinforces her status and he says, "I have
children," so then he's believed because he's continuing to make her מותר,
mutar, which is our presumption of her. יש לי אחי אינו נאמן,
yesh li achi eino ne'eman, but if he says he has brothers
he's not believed. לאו כל כמיניה דאסר לה אכל עלמא. lav kol
kemeinei de'asar la akol alma. He's not believed to make her forbidden.
So the basic point of the משנה Mishna therefore is not so
much that he's believed to make her מותר mutar or not אסור,
assur, but he's not believed to go against the status quo, the
חזקה, Hazakah, our presumption. If what he's saying is consistent with the
presumption that she's מותר, mutar, then he is believed. Now, how about
the ברייתא Baraita that says he's believed even to make her forbidden
according to רבי נתן Rebbe Natan on his deathbed? ברייתא Baraita דמוחזק
לן באחי ולא מוחזק לן בבני. demuchzak lan be'achei velo muchzak lan
bevanai. So that we know that he has brothers and we don't
and but and we don't know that he has sons, meaning so
we start presuming that she's obligated in יבום. Yibbum. Okay, now that's
what happened before he was about to marry her. All right, remember
and then he said if the ברייתא Baraita was he said one
thing at the time of the קידושין Kiddushin to make to say
that she's מותר mutar and the opposite at the deathbed. So before
he was basically interested in marrying her, we were presuming that he
had brothers. And then he said to her, "I don't have brothers."
And we were prepared to believe him. Now why were we prepared
to believe him at the time of marriage when he said, "I
don't have brothers," which goes against our
presumption? דאמרינן מה לי לשקר de'amrinan mah lo leshaker because we say,
"Look, if he's telling her he doesn't have brothers and now we
could say you know maybe he's lying he's trying to get her
to agree to marry him. No, he wouldn't lie. Why wouldn't he
lie? Because מאי קאמר לה מאיסטרא דיבום? mai ka'amar la meistra deyibbum?
You'll say he's lying in order to get out of יבום? Yibbum?
מה דאמר פטרינא לך בגיטא. mai de'amar patreina lach begitah. He could
have just said that I'll get you out I'll give you a
גט. Get. So the fact that we presume that this is so
now we're starting to believe why do we believe him. So our
משנה Mishna according to the way we're setting it up says really
very little. Our משנה Mishna says we believe him to reinforce the
status quo, not go against the status quo, not say that she's
אסור. assur. Okay, so whereas in our case we're actually taking in
the ברייתא Baraita we're making a bigger חידוש. hiddush. Okay, and in
the case of the ברייתא Baraita is how did these things go?
דמוחזק לן באחי muchzak lan be'achei means that he actually knew he
had No, no
no not that we knew, we presumed. So if we knew if
we knew we assumed. What? Yeah, people were talking about it, "Oh,
you don't you know he's got a brother somewhere," but like nobody's
giving any direct testimony. Okay, so this is the קידושין Kiddushin and
this is the deathbed. Okay, these are the two times. So here
we basically okay we presumed he's got a brother. Okay, and he
says no brother. Okay, now the logic thing is to think that
he's saying it just to get her to agree to marry him.
Okay, and the first חידוש hiddush is that we actually do believe
her to change the חזקה Hazakah and to now presume that she
would not be obligated in יבום. Yibbum. Why? Because it's מה לי
לשקר. mah lo leshaker. Now why she ah, oh come on, he's
not lying. If he was just trying to promise her that there
wouldn't be יבום, Yibbum, he could always tell her, "You know what?
We'll arrange..." whole thing, I'll give you a גט get that'll take
effect a minute before I die, etc., etc. Okay, so because we're
saying, "Oh, there's not a good enough reason to lie," it's actually
quite a big חידוש, chiddush, even when there's a presumption that she's
obligated in יבום, yibbum, he's believed to go against that. That's stage
number one: why the ברייתא braita assumes that we believe him. Now
how come here when he says, "I have a brother," okay, "I
have a brother," okay, that's what he says on his deathbed here,
he'll have him on his deathbed, okay. So, so רבי Rebbi says
not believed, and רבי נתן Rebbi Nosson says he is believed. Now
what's the issue here? Okay. So now you understand why רבי נתן
Rebbi Nosson is more likely to say he's believed, because we started
with a presumption, maybe his statement was enough to neutralize it, and
that was the big חידוש chiddush that now we can assume that
she's permitted, but now he's going back to the original presumption. So
if this was
like a close tie here, this is tipping our scales back to
our original presumption, okay. And רבי Rebbi says no, מה לי לשקר
mah li l'shaker says so much that we totally preferred to believe
him that we completely shifted our presumption here and she's now completely
assumed to be non-obligated in יבום, yibbum, and now, and now he's
not believed to change her status quo to make a woman who
we assume to be permitted to make her forbidden on his say-so.
So let's read that.
I know, so you could do the מה לי לשקר mah li
l'shaker again. So let's read it again. רבי Rebbi סבר savar מה
לי לשקר mah li l'shaker כעדים דמי. k'eidim dami. The first מה
לי לשקר mah li l'shaker was like witnesses, ואתו עדים אקרי חזקה,
v'asu eidim akri chazakah,
so that first time he said that I'm married totally uprooted the
חזקה chazakah and made us totally presume that she was, that she
was not obligated in יבום. yibbum. Now, of course the second question
obviously is, but now there's a second מה לי לשקר. mah li
l'shaker. But, you know, but it's not the same מה לי לשקר.
mah li l'shaker. Here מה לי לשקר mah li l'shaker was why
would he lie, he would have another way to do it, to
promise that he could give her a גט. get. Here, you know,
who knows, maybe he's lying, maybe he wants to just, they were
fighting and his last act he wants to do on this earth
is to make her miserable, and there's no מה לי לשקר mah
li l'shaker because he couldn't achieve it in another way. Here he
could have achieved it by promising to give her a גט get
that would take effect a minute before. So there's not exactly a
מה לי לשקר mah li l'shaker here. You understand why? Okay. So,
you know, you could say, "Come on, by the context he's probably
just trying to come clean," but nevertheless that's what רבי Rebbi says.
So this trumped, I can't use the word trumped
anymore, anyway, and then, so now, now he cannot once she's presumed
מותר mutter he can't make her אסור, assur, that's what רבי Rebbi
says. רבי נתן Rebbi Nosson סבר savar no, מה לי לשקר mah
li l'shaker כחזקה דמי. k'chazakah dami. No, no, no, it was only
enough to neutralize the pre-existing חזקה, chazakah, and the little bit we
were tipping in that side, but לא אתי חזקה ואקרי חזקה לגמרי,
lo asi chazakah v'akri chazakah l'gamrei, it did not completely erase the
original חזקה, chazakah, and now when he goes back to reinforcing the
original חזקה chazakah we believe him. So a little complicated and I
want to get onto the next topic, but the basic point of
this is that the גמרא Gemara says that it helps us understand,
thank you, why we should believe him. Number one, if what he's
saying is reinforcing her status of being מותר, mutter, of course we
believe him. Number two, if she has the status of מותר mutter
and he's just saying she's אסור, assur, the גמרא Gemara is saying
even רבי נתן Rebbi Nosson would say, you know, on your say-so,
you do not have the power to make your wife who's presumed
to not be obligated in יבום yibbum just because of some claim
you're making, first now to bind her, to make her forbidden. Okay?
So you're not believed for if she has a חזקה chazakah of
being מותר, mutter, you're not believed to make her אסור. assur. And
even that's the presumption of our משנה, Mishnah, but the גמרא, Gemara,
if you want to think big picture what the גמרא Gemara is
doing is the גמרא Gemara is neutralizing the position of רבי נתן.
Rebbi Nosson. It sounded like רבי נתן Rebbi Nosson says the man
is believed to say that his wife is obligated in יבום, yibbum,
and the גמרא Gemara is saying no, that's not true. If she
has a חזקה, chazakah, a presumption of being מותר, mutter, he is
not believed even according to רבי נתן. Rebbi Nosson. The only time
רבי נתן Rebbi Nosson believes her is when what he is saying
is reinforcing a pre-existing חזקה chazakah that we'd had, okay, that was
somewhat neutralized in the middle. All right, and that would be the
case of the debate. Also מה לי לשקר mah li l'shaker can
also be challenged, although maybe with a more modern sensibility, but maybe
I would rather get married to somebody who has
no brother because I don't want to be mixed up in יבום
yibbum with somebody who I didn't want to marry. Right. No, but
the point is that he could always promise to her give her
a גט get that would take effect a minute before. I know,
that's not exactly the same as not having the problem to begin
with. I understand, it's not so clear. All right, let's go onto
the next משנה. Mishnah. The גמרא Gemara is using מה לי לשקר,
mah li l'shaker, it's really מיגו, migo, right? Or is that how
you use it? Yeah, מה לי לשקר, mah li l'shaker, there's a
general discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim that מיגו migo and מה לי
לשקר mah li l'shaker are often used interchangeably. There's an attempt sometimes
to distinguish between them, but they're pretty similar. Okay. Okay, so, yeah.
Can this misinformation, if it is misinformation, annul the marriage, that she
wouldn't marry him?
Oh, yeah, that's an interesting point. If he's lying and deceiving her,
then would we basically say that... actually is an interesting possibility. That's
a possibility that it'd be like a מקח טעות Mekach Ta'ut in
some circumstances. Okay. Now המקדש. Hamekadesh. So that was dealing with who
do you believe, right? If he says, here's, if a father says
that I married off my daughter, if a guy is talking about
whether he has brothers or children. Now we have a question before
we get to believing whether something happened or not, similar to the
issue before, the guy said "I married my daughter and I don't
know to who," and a guy showed up, etc. Remember that case
where he didn't know who the man he married his daughter to?
Here there's a question, he forgot which of his many daughters he
married off. Okay. So let's take a look. המקדש את בתו סתם,
Hamekadesh et bito stam, a man marries his daughter and he doesn't
say which daughter he's marrying, and he has more than one. אין
בבוגרת בכלל, Ein babogeret bechlal, it doesn't include the daughters that are
more than twelve and a half years old that are
mature, because, which is pretty obvious, he doesn't have a right to
marry them off. So that seems very obvious and the גמרא's Gemara
going to ask what's that even teaching us? Now here becomes the
thing we're going to focus on a little bit more. מי שיש
לו שתי כיתי בנות משתי נשים, Mi sheyesh lo shtei kitei banot
mishtei nashim,
a man had two wives. Okay. Sequentially, not at the same time.
Okay. So wife number one, and he had two daughters, or actually
he says two sets of daughters, two groups of daughters from each
wife. Okay. So the older daughters and the younger daughters. Okay. So
they're two groups. ואמר, Ve'amar, he says, קידשתי את בתי הגדולה, Kidashti
et biti hagedolah, I married my oldest daughter, my older daughter. Okay.
Normally I think we'd probably translate it as oldest, but let's take
a look. ואיני יודע אם גדולה שבגדולות או גדולה שבקטנות או קטנה
שבגדולות שהיא גדולה מן הגדולה שבקטנות. Ve'eini yodeia im gedolah shebagedolot o
gedolah shebaketanot o ktanah shebagedolot shehi gedolah min hagedolah shebaketanot. Okay, sorry,
I don't know which. Okay.
So here are the
daughters. Okay. These are his two oldest daughters, and these are the
two youngest daughters. Okay. This is his new wife, this is wife
number one, and this is wife number two. They're sequential, they're not
wives at the same
time. So he said the oldest. So this is the older group,
and this is the younger group. Okay. So he says, I don't
know which one I meant. Did I mean the oldest of the
oldest? Or did I mean the oldest of the youngest, but I
called her oldest because she was from the oldest group of daughters?
I could have even meant the youngest, or maybe I meant the
oldest in the youngest group. Okay. Any one of those could go
on by the word oldest because either these are from the oldest
group and this one, make this a tiny little baby anyway, and
this one is the oldest of the youngest group. So ואיני יודע,
Ve'eini yodeia, and I don't know, okay, אם גדולה שבגדולות, im gedolah
shebagedolot,
the oldest of the oldest group, או גדולה שבקטנות, o gedolah shebaketanot,
or the older of the youngest group, או קטנה שבגדולות, o ktanah
shebagedolot, or even the youngest one of the oldest group, שהיא גדולה
מן הגדולה שבקטנות, shehi gedolah min hagedolah shebaketanot, who is still older
than the oldest one of the youngest group. כולן אסורות. Kulan asurot.
So they're all they might be the daughter married off and they're
all forbidden, חוץ מן הקטנה שבקטנות, chutz min haktanah shebaketanot, except for
the youngest of the youngest group because there's no way that could
be called old. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir, this is what
Rabbi Meir says. רבי יוסי אומר כולן מותרות. Rabbi Yossi omer kulan
mutarot. No, they're all permissible. חוץ מן הגדולה שבגדולות, Chutz min hagedolah
shebagedolot, except the oldest of the oldest, because Rabbi Yossi says you
would never have used a phrase or you would never have remembered
it in a way that would have led to such ambiguity. So
the thing that you remembered was oldest, you must mean the most
narrow, the most specific thing defined by oldest, which is the oldest
of the oldest. Okay. קידשתי את בתי הקטנה ואיני יודע אם קטנה
שבקטנות או קטנה שבגדולות. Kidashti et biti haktanah ve'eini yodeia im ktanah
shebaketanot o ktanah shebagedolot. Okay, statement of the reverse. Okay. I married
my youngest daughter and I don't know if it is the youngest
of the youngest group or the youngest of the oldest group, או
גדולה שבקטנות, o gedolah shebaketanot, or the oldest of the youngest group,
שהיא קטנה מן הקטנה שבגדולות, shehi ktanah min haktanah shebagedolot, that is
still younger than the youngest one of the older group. I got
a little confused. Anyway, כולן אסורות, Kulan asurot, they're all forbidden, חוץ
מן הגדולה שבגדולות. chutz min hagedolah shebagedolot.
So any one of them could mean youngest, either of these could
be youngest because they're in the youngest group, and this could be
youngest relative because of the older group she's the youngest, except for
חוץ מן הגדולה שבגדולות, chutz min hagedolah shebagedolot, the oldest of the
oldest group. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יוסי אומר כולן
מותרות, Rabbi Yossi omer kulan mutarot, they're all permissible, חוץ מן הקטנה
שבקטנות, chutz min haktanah shebaketanot, except the youngest if while you said
or all you can remember is youngest, then you mean what that
means in the most unambiguous way, which is youngest of the youngest.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, הקטנות. haketanot. So the
first thing we're going to look at is the first line of
the משנה. Mishnah. He marries off his daughter, one of his daughters.
Okay. And he doesn't know which one. It's not meaning he so
the difference of the first line of the משנה Mishnah and the
second is that the second cases of the משנה Mishnah is he
knew which one at the time, but he forgot what he meant.
Okay. Or he forgot what he said. That's the second case about
oldest and youngest and all of that. The first case is he
didn't even specify at the time. I'm marrying my daughter to you.
Great. And he gave me a ring. End of story. Oh, well
we don't include the oldest. It's clearly not the oldest daughter because
I don't or it's clearly not the בוגרת bogeret because I don't
have the rights to marry her off. But in that case, it
was never specified which daughter. And this gets to the גמרא's Gemara
question about
קידושין שאינם. kiddushin she'einam. So when you gave me a ring for
one of my daughters and we didn't say which one, so okay
fine, it doesn't include the ones that I don't have a right
to marry off, the ones that are already adults, okay. But it
might be any one of the youngest ones. But how could that
be? We don't know which one. And therefore it's a קידושין שאינם
מסורים לביאה. Kiddushin she-einam mesurim l'viah. It's a קידושין Kiddushin which you'll
never be able to culminate in actually having sex because you might
always be having sex with the sister of the woman you're actually
married to. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: הקטנות בכלל? Ha-ktanos bichlal?
Does that mean that the underaged daughters are all potentially married to
this guy when you don't know which, when you just said it
without specifying? שמע מינה—or Shma mina it sounds like that—שמע מינה Shma
mina can we infer from
this: קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה הוי קידושין? Kiddushin she-einam mesurim l'viah havei
Kiddushin? That a קידושין Kiddushin that can never culminate in sex is
still קידושין? Kiddushin? Okay, 'cause that's what it would sound like, because
it sounds like you're ספק Safek married to any one of the
underaged daughters. No, הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha b'mai askinan, what are we
talking about? כשאין שם אלא גדולה וקטנה. K'she-ein sham ela gedola u-ktana.
No, you don't have multiple daughters, you know, a lot of underaged
daughters. You have an adult daughter and an underaged daughter. So the
גמרא Gemara says: והבוגרות קתני? V'ha-bogros katani? It says the adult daughters
are not included. Sounds like you have multiple daughters. And so the
גמרא Gemara says: והבוגרות קתני—no, V'ha-bogros katani מאי בוגרות בוגרות דעלמא. Mai
bogros bogros d'alma. It means—it doesn't mean you have adult daughters. It
means when a person says, "I'm marrying you my daughter," he's not
referring to adult daughters. It doesn't mean the use of the plural
doesn't mean this man has multiple daughters. It means in cases where
people talk about this, they're not referring to the adult daughters, they're
only referring to the underaged daughters. Okay, but can he be referring
to those adult daughters in any case? Well that's the גמרא's Gemara
going to get to that. What's the חידוש Chidush at all? But
the first point we're saying
is that when we say he's married to the younger daughter, it's
only one daughter. If it was daughters, he wouldn't be married because
it would not be a קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה. Kiddushin she-einam mesurim
l'viah. We'll get to what the חידוש Chidush is in a minute.
Okay. But first we're just dealing with the fact that we have
to say the משנה Mishnah is talking about there's only one underaged
daughter, not multiple ones, and therefore the use of the plural is—doesn't
mean—it means we're talking about like in cases where, and we're not
talking about in this specific case that a man has multiple underaged
daughters. So the גמרא Gemara says: פשיטא בוגרות מאי עבידתייהו? Peshita bogros
mai avidataihu? And now the גמרא Gemara says that: If the point
was to say he's married to one of the underaged daughters and
the חידוש Chidush would have been that קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה Kiddushin
she-einam mesurim l'viah still takes effect, but if the case is there's
only one underaged daughter and only one adult daughter, so there's no
חידוש. Chidush. Of course it's not the adult daughter. He doesn't have
the right to marry the adult daughter. הכא במאי עסקינן—no, Hacha b'mai
askinan here's the חידוש—דשויתיה שליח, Shaliach that the adult daughter made him
a שליח Shaliach. to find her a husband. So in that case
he's empowered to marry both his adult daughter and his underaged daughter.
And that's the חידוש. Chidush The father—the father's a שליח. Shaliach, Exactly.
And now the father's empowered to marry both his adult daughter and
his underaged daughter. And that's the חידוש. Chidush. מהו דתימא כי מקבל
קידושי אדעתא דידה קמקבל, Mahu d'teima ki mekabel kiddushey adaita didah ka
mekabel, when he marries off a daughter and he doesn't say which
one, presumably he's referring to the adult daughter.
Right, I would think so, I mean for us that would make
more sense. We would consider the adult daughter more of a marriageable
age. No, קא משמע לן לא שביק איניש מידי דאית ליה הנאה
מיניה ועביד מידי דלית ליה הנאה מיניה. Kamashma lan lo shavik inish
midi d'is lei hana-ei minei v'avid midi d'leis lei hana-ei minei. He's
not going to abandon something that he can make some profit off
of and do something he doesn't make profit. Why? Because when he
marries off his underaged daughter, he keeps the ring. When he marries
off his adult daughter, he has to give her the ring. So
obviously he was marrying off his younger daughter because he wants to
keep the money for the קידושין. Kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says:
Wait a minute, really? מיזו עסקינן דאמרה ליה קידושי לך? Mizu askinan
d'amra lei kiddushey lach? If we're talking about a scenario where the
adult daughter made her—his her שליח, Shaliach, him her שליח, presumably it
would even be if she said: And you know what, you can
even keep the כסף קידושין Kesef Kiddushin for your efforts. Okay, and
so would you say and then nevertheless, presumably it would include that
case. So would that case also why should she be married, why
should we assume he's marrying only the younger one? אפילו הכי לא
שביק איניש מצוה דרמיא עליה ועביד מצוה דלא רמיא עליה. Afillu hachi
lo shavik inish mitzvah d'ramya alei v'avid mitzvah d'lo ramya alei. Nevertheless,
even though there's no benefit, monetary benefit of marrying off the younger
one before the older one—I mean the younger one before the older
one—nevertheless the younger one is more his responsibility. Why is it more
his responsibility? Because while the child is still underaged, it's the father's
responsibility to make sure they're taken care of. And for his daughter
it means there's a responsibility to make sure he's got them a
husband. Okay, so the father—so it's an interest completely obviously different reality
than we live in, where he's more responsible and he would feel
more of a priority to marry off his daughter under the age
of 12 than his 13-year-old or 16-year-old daughter or whatever. Okay, but
that's the reality, that's why he was empowered—is empowered to marry her.
It's a society in which you have to make sure she has
a husband and protected, and he does that while she's under his
control. And you know, the way the תורה Torah envisions it, of
course, is that a girl is either בבית אביה B'veit aviha or
בבית בעלה. B'veit ba'alah. Like there's—like the whole idea, I should take
a second to point that out, I said it before, which is
that a girl can have independence and not— not have her father
controlling her or her husband controlling her. In the תורה *Torah* you
only have that basically after her husband dies. Okay? Or divorces her.
And you never have it while the she's like an, you know,
a young adult and she's free or even an adult and, you
know, and free from because the תורה *Torah* assumes she goes straight
from her father's house into her husband's house. Right? It's only that
the rabbis say, wait, wait, wait, there's that would be only if
she's under age, you know, but once she's at the age of
a בוגרת *Bogeret*, right? Then she actually can be in she can
have left one without going into the other. But that never is
a scenario in the תורה *Torah*. So therefore the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying is, you know, the father's responsibility is that she go
from the father's house to the husband's house. So his primary responsibility
is to marry off his underage daughters, not his adult daughters. Yes,
Charlie. Reminded of לבן *Lavan*. Yeah, about we only marry the older
daughter. Yeah, well that's for the second part of the משנה Mishnah.
*Mishnah* particularly. But yes. Here we're talking about adults versus underage or
about to get to older versus younger. Okay, so that's the first
part of the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, that if he did if he
had multiple daughters and he did not specify, then, and they were
all underage, then maybe they're not married at all because the marriage
cannot culminate in sex. But if it's an adult and a and
an underage, even if he's empowered to marry both, we assume he's
only marrying the younger one. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
Now we get to the bigger, more, you know, fun part about
two sets of daughters. And by the way, in this case of
all these two sets, they all have to be all under the
age of, all קטנה ketana *Ketannah* or נערה *Naarah*, or else he
couldn't be marrying them. Okay? So this one is, you know, this
one here is eleven and this one is ten and this one
is three and this one is one. Right? But they're all under
the age of בת bas מצווה *Bat Mitzvah*. Well, or under, not,
you know, they're still a נערה *Naarah*. Okay. All right. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: מי שקידש שתי בנות *Mi she-kidesh
shtei bnot*. So first we have the case about when he said
about what does he mean by oldest and then we had what
does he mean when he said youngest. Or, וצריכא *Ve-tzricha*. You need
to do both scenarios even though they're pretty much the same. אי
Ei אשמעינן קמייתא *Iy ashmienan kamaisa*, if we had just the case
about oldest, דהכא אמר רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *D-hakha amar Rabbi Meir*,
דכיון דאיכא de-ika זוטרא מינה *D-keivan d-ika zutra mina*, להך גדולה gedola
קרי לה *L-hakh gdola kari lah*.
That anyone of these he could call the oldest, because as long
as there's somebody younger. Okay, that we understand. אבל Aval בהא *Aval
be-ha*, but when you say younger or youngest, אימא aima מודי ליה
לרבי יוסי *Eima modi leh l-Rabbi Yossi*, דקטינה דכולהו קרי לה *D-ktina
d-khulhu kari lah*. Youngest you would only say the very youngest. You
wouldn't call this one the youngest. Now why would it be different?
Why
would you call a middle one older because there's somebody younger than
them, but you wouldn't call a middle one younger because there's somebody
because there's somebody older than them? So רש״י *Rashi* basically says, you
know, younger is like it's not as nice of a category to
be in the youngest category. Who likes to be the youngest child?
Everybody wants to be older, or you know, presumably. Always be the
princess. I suppose. Anyway, so therefore the way רש״י *Rashi* explains it
is, you're more likely to use the word גדולה gedola, *Gdola* older
a little more liberally, right? To include somebody who's not the oldest,
but at least relatively older. But you could say you're less likely
to use the word younger or youngest unless it means the very
youngest. And nevertheless we say no, even when he's saying youngest, anyone
of these can be considered to be the youngest except for this
one. I think really the kid would want to be considered younger.
Right, right. Well also if you're marrying her off, maybe if she's
so young she's not so usable as a wife, you know, until
she gets a little older. Anyway. Okay. ואי Ve-i אמר בהא בהא
קאמר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Ve-iy amar be-ha be-ha ka-amar Rabbi Yossi*.
Now if you had just said the case of youngest and you
told me the חידוש Chidush. *Chidush* that even by youngest רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says it could mean anybody except the oldest.
Fine, that's where רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi Yossi* says no, no,
no, no, youngest means only the very youngest. אבל בהא *Aval be-ha*,
but when you say גדולה gedola. *Gdola*, you know, oldest or older,
אימא מודי ליה לרבי מאיר *Eima modi leh l-Rabbi Meir*, maybe they
would agree to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* that older could
mean anybody because except the very youngest because older is a more
positive description and you'd more rather call even a middle child older.
צריכא *Tzricha*, so you have to tell me they debate both cases.
Okay. By the way, this partly this plays off with I think
an ambiguity in Hebrew, right? Because how would you say there's no
one word that you could say older as opposed to oldest, right?
You could say הכי גדולה gedola, *Hachi gdola*, right? But גדולה gedola
*Gdola* does that mean the older or the oldest daughter? That's the
part of the ambiguity here, right? Okay. In certain cases you could
say הבכירה *Ha-bechira*. That's
true. Okay, right. That's for the one second. Right, unless there's also
small.
Well you don't know, maybe there's also boys that are older. Okay,
so okay. למימרא *L-meimra*, now, now we're going to get to the
core of the debate. למימרא דרבי מאיר סבר savar מכניס אינש נפשיה
לספיקא *L-meimra d-Rabbi Meir savar machnis inash nafshiah l-sfeika*. So this says
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says the person is willing
to get themselves into this ambiguous space, bring themselves into a doubt,
meaning that they could use a phrase, again it's a little not
clear to me is whether the phrase older or oldest is what
he said at the time of the קידושין Kiddushin, *Kiddushin*, or whether
it doesn't sound like that. It sounds like at the time it
was clear who he meant and now he forgot, but what he
remembers is, he forgot specifically who he was talking about but he
remembers it was the oldest. So it sounds like, you know, you
don't remember something, we assume what you you're going to remember in
this way that's more specific, that doesn't leave you in this gray,
in this, you know, uncertain and this gray zone. Okay, so that
sounds like רבי מאיר says that a person no, you know, people
might remember big- oldest in the way like, like if you're afraid
you're going to forget, you'll say wait, I gotta remember, when I
go back to tell my wife who I marry off, it was
Rachel, right, that's who I married off. That's what you'll tell yourself
because you want to remember who it is. You're not going to
say, oh tell her it was the oldest one, unless you can
remember what oldest means, unless oldest is very clear and well-defined. So
רבי מאיר says no, people are sloppy and they'll remember oldest, little
matters like marriage, exactly, and they'll remember oldest or youngest even if
it's not specific and it could mean a couple of people. Okay,
so I guess with all these scenarios where a guy comes home
drunk. אוי, Oy, okay, could be. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi סבר לא
מחזיק
אינש נפשיה בספיקא. lo machzik inish nafshye besafika. No,
people do not get themselves into doubt and if he's remembering this,
it only can- it'll only mean the most specific thing. ואיפכא שמעינן
להו. Ve'ifka sham'inan lehu. One minute, we teach in a ברייתא Beraita
the exact reverse. דתנן, Detnan, הנודר עד הפסח, hanoder ad HaPesach, אסור
עד שיגיע. asur ad sheyagia.
If somebody says, this- these fruit are forbidden to me until Pesach,
so until means until- once Pesach arrives, once Pesach arrives, it's permissible.
עד שיהא הפסח, Ad sheyehei HaPesach,
until Pesach occurs, okay, אסור עד שיצא. asur ad sheyeitzei.
Then it means until it occurs means until we're done with Pesach,
so it's forbidden until Pesach is over. Regardless of what he intended
in this case, right? No, that's always the question. Parsing words and
it's דברים שבלב, devarim shebalev, but by נדרים nedarim we go more
by דברים שבלב, devarim shebalev, but anyway this is the default. We
can worry another time if he says he meant something else. עד
פני הפסח, Ad pnei HaPesach, now let's say he says until the
face of Pesach. What does that mean? רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir
omer, אסור עד שיגיע, asur ad sheyagia, until Pesach arrives. רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, עד שיצא, ad sheyeitzei, until it leaves. And
what we assume they're debating is that the very- it's sort of
like oldest and youngest. The first face, the first face that Pesach
presents to me is the first day. But then there's another face
of Pesach, the second day, and then there's another face. Every next
day is presenting, as it were, its face to me. I would
say ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. Well, okay, right. But that's- you mean
the- okay, but the face here means the actual Pesach itself. If
you think about the days of Pesach presenting themselves to you. Anyway,
so we see this as a similar debate and their positions are
reversed. Okay? רבי מאיר says that it means the most specific thing,
the first face of Pesach. And רבי יוסי says it could mean
any of them and you're forbidden the entire time. So it seems
like it's exact reverse position. אמר רב חנינא בר אבדימי אמר רב,
Amar Rav Chanina bar Avdimi amar Rav, מוחלפת השיטה. muchlefet hashita. You're
right, the names got reversed, okay, and they really- you know, now-
and you have to flip it. Okay. Never mind, you didn't know
which door, you don't know which- I know, it's true, I- I
realize that, yeah. והתניא, Vehatanya, we turned a ברייתא Beraita that actually
flips the names of the Pesach debate to be consistent with our
משנה. Mishnah And here's what the ברייתא Beraita says. Wait, Rabbi- Rabbi
Lintsner? I don't- I don't get how that's going to help. The
original מחלוקת machlokes they were trying to clarify by the comparison to
this נדר neder is whether or not one of them holds that
people are sloppy or not sloppy. Right. Here in the issue of
the נדר, neder, it's not an issue of being sloppy or not
sloppy, there's an exactitude they're only debating what the exactitude means. No,
because that's what I was saying. So רש"י Rashi says that the
גמרא Gemara presumes that פני הפסח pnei HaPesach can refer to any-
to any day of Pesach because every day is a- is a
face. It's like- it's like the- the- that day is presenting itself
to you, right? So- so therefore the same way the word גדולה
gedola can mean any daughter who can be labeled with גדולה, gedola
any day could be labeled as it's a face of Pesach, one
of the faces of Pesach. Oh, I see. It's like a day-
like if you said a day of Pesach, if you said a
day of Pesach it could mean the first day, it could mean
any day. Okay, so, so okay, so the גמרא Gemara says and
the ברייתא Beraita reverses the positions to be consistent with our
משנה. Mishnah והתניא, Vehatanya, here והתניא vehatanya is used as a- as
a statement, not as a challenge. זה הכלל, Ze haklal, כל שזמנו
קבוע kol shezemano kavua ואמר עד פני, ve'amar ad pnei, anything that
has a fixed amount of time and you say until the face
of it, רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, עד שיצא, ad sheyeitzei,
until it's gone- until it's finished. So רבי מאיר says that's doubtful
what that means, it could mean a whole wide range of things,
so it's- I mean it could mean any day so it's until
the period is done. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, עד שיגיע.
ad sheyagia. Nope, until- once it arrives, that's the first face, that's
what you mean. So רבי יוסי says you don't sort of enter
into a space of doubt, רבי מאיר says you do. Yes, Charlie.
By the opinion that it would apply through all of Pesach, this
would be a נדר neder that would cause you to not fulfill
a positive rabbinic- you could what? About- שמחת יום טוב? simchas yom
tov? ארבע כוסות? arba kosos? How do you know what you're talking
about? You didn't say wine, you said- some- fruit. You said- you
said fruit, right? It doesn't say- oh, it doesn't say what you're
אסר-ing. aser Oh, if you're אסר-ing aser wine, נו, nu, okay, we'll
worry about that some other time. Okay, anyway, a נדר neder can
undermine even מצוות דאורייתא. mitzvos de'oraisa. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מחלוקת, machlokes, now we're going to get
back to the debate in the משנה Mishnah and actually have a-
quite a- have a nice clarification. בשתי כיתי בנות, Bishtei kitei banot,
it's true only specifically to the case of the משנה Mishnah where
there's two groups and this could be anybody in this group could
be called oldest because it's the oldest group. Anybody in this group
could be called youngest because it's the youngest group. And that's what
makes it possible that it could be anybody except you know except
the extremes. It says אבל בכת אחת, b'kat achas, if it's like
one group, he's got ten kids or four kids or whatever it
is, גדולה ממש וקטנה ממש אמצעית בשמה קרי לה. gedola mamash u'ketana
mamash emtza'is bishma kari la. So let's say a guy has four
kids, okay,
four daughters, okay, he's got these four daughters in this age order,
right? Okay, and he says גדולה. gedola So there's no way that
anybody here is called גדולה, gedola right? Yes, she's older relative to
a younger one, but the word גדולה gedola would not be relevant
here. Here you would only describe the middle ones as middle daughters.
So if you wanted to talk about a middle daughter you'd use
her name. גדולה gedola means the oldest and קטנה ketana means the
youngest. Here גדולה gedola can mean oldest because she's גדולה gedola within
the universe of this group, she's the oldest, and גדולה gedola here
and this even she could be גדולה gedola because this is a
group that is גדולה from the other group. Everyone in the oldest
group,
everyone is older than everybody else. Yes, correct. So although גדולה means
oldest, Abaye says, not older, so if there's all one group only
one is the oldest. But if there's two groups she's the oldest
within this group and anyone here is oldest in the sense of
from the oldest group. Okay. And then he says אמצעית emtza'is and
there's a middle too. Right. Then it's קידושין שאינם מסורין לביאה kiddushin
she'einam mesurin l'viah or whatever. The point is that the word גדולה
could be describing the word כת. kat. Right, exactly, בת מהכת הגדולה
bas me'hakat hagedola
or the בת from the כת הגדולה, kat hagedola, right, exactly.
Okay. So
thankfully the גמרא Gemara doesn't ask that, okay, but presumably it would
be not obviously not referred to because the label קטנה ktana or
גדולה doesn't refer to it.
Right, I guess so, that would be true. That would be true.
Okay. אמר ליה רב אדא בר מתנה לאביי אלא מעתה, Amar lei
Rav Adda bar Masna l'Abaye ella me'ata, Rav Adda bar Masna says
to Abaye, if that's true, אמצעית
שבכת שנייה תשתרי. emtza'is she'b'kat shniya tishari. So he says I've been
making it easy and describing that there are only two in each
group but he says let's say there are three in each group.
Okay. Now in that case, okay, when you say oldest we thought
it meant even this, we thought not like Abaye, it meant anybody
that was older than anybody else, okay, and then it would only
and then the only one excluded would be number one. But according
to
Abaye, no no, it means oldest and you have to be able
to attach the label oldest. If there were three in this group
this one would be okay, it would only apply to the oldest
of that group. And Abaye's answer's going to be you're right, okay,
but let's take a look. But the משנה Mishnah says the only
one permissible is the youngest one. So his question is well I
don't understand why isn't number two permissible because within this group oldest
can only refer to number three. But you're referring to two and
two. Well the משנה Mishnah didn't say that. I've been saying that.
The משנה Mishnah says there are שתי כיתות shtei kittei and it
does... Alright, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara. says
אלא מעתה אמצעית שבכת שנייה תשתרי. ella me'ata emtza'is she'b'kat shniya tishari.
הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha b'mai askinan, top of ס"ה, samech-hei, בשאין שם
אלא גדולה וקטנה, b'she'ein sham ella gedola u'ketana, there's only two in
the youngest group. Okay. דהכי נמי מסתברא, De'hachi nami mistabra, you know
that makes sense. דאי סלקא דעתך דאיכא, De'ee salka dachlach de'ika, if
there really were three in the youngest group, לישתרי, lishari, then tell
us, don't tell us everybody is... then don't tell us the oldest
is okay, right. Remember he says I don't know if I meant
the oldest of the youngest group, right. According to if there really
were three he should have said I don't know if I meant
the middle of the youngest group, right. The fact that it doesn't
talk about a middle one shows we're not talking about it. Okay.
So the
גמרא Gemara says ולטעמיך, u'l'ta'ameicha, one minute, according to that argument, אמצעית
שבכת ראשונה דודאי ספיקא הוי תשתרי, emtza'is she'b'kat rishona d'vaday sefeika hvei
tishari, מי קתני? mi kasni? One minute, let's say there was another
one here, okay, let's say right let's say there were three here,
okay, and he said and he said oldest. All three would be
אסור, assur, right? Because they're all from the oldest group. So but
the משנה Mishnah doesn't say that, the משנה Mishnah only talks about
the oldest and the youngest being אסור. assur. So it doesn't talk
about a middle. So obviously we're... there could be middle girls that
are אסור assur that we're not talking about. So so you could
say that in the youngest group as well. So the גמרא Gemara
says מי
קתני, mi kasni, it doesn't speak about a middle one in the
oldest group. מאי קושיא, Mai kushya, what kind of question is that?
התם תנא קטנה דאזלא לאיסורא. Hasam tanna ketana d'azla l'issura. Here it
says the oldest and the youngest are אסור. assur. So it doesn't
have to tell you the middle one is אסור, assur, right. Remember
the משנה Mishnah says I don't know if I meant the oldest
of the oldest group or the youngest of the other group, right.
So if it says this is... So if it says this is
אסור assur and this one is אסור, assur, of course this one
is אסור, assur, so it doesn't have to mention it. But here
it says it only mentions that this one is אסור, assur, so
implicitly anybody younger than the oldest one is going to be מותר.
muttar. Okay. התם תנא קטנה דגדל איסורא Hatam tana ktana degadal issura
והוא הדין לאחרי דקשישא
מינה, vehu hadin leachda d'kashisha mina, it would include the other, the
one older than the youngest. הכא אם איתא, Hacha i itika, if
there was a middle one that would be forbidden,
ניתני איהי. nisnei ihi. Okay, so basically אביי Abaye makes a very
good read of the משנה Mishnah, that it does not mean anybody
who is relatively older than somebody else, it means anybody you can
attach the label oldest to, and because there are two groups, that
it's that you can attach it to a broader number of people.
אמרי רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרבא, Amrei Rav Huna brei d'Rav
Yehoshua l'Rava, הפסח דכי קתני אחת דמי ופליגי, HaPesach d'ki kas achas
dami upligi, one minute he says, if that's true, when you says
עד פני הפסח, at pnei HaPesach,
right, that we said that that was the same debate, and we
were assuming that why is it? Because you have like the seven
days of פסח, Pesach,
right,
if you think that each day, here I'm going to sort of,
you know, each day gives its פני pnei to you, right? That's
the idea of the פני pnei here you are, you're entering in
and until you hit the פני pnei of פסח. Pesach. So any
one of these can be the פני pnei of פסח, Pesach, so
it's אסור assur until the end, that's what we said. But that's
a case where that's like one group of a lot of children,
right? So there's only one has the first פני, pnei, right? So
according to אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye says the only reason is because
there's two groups and each one you can sort of attach the
label oldest to. But this, only one of them presents its first
פני pnei to you, why does it apply, why is every day
part of the ספק? safek? The first day of פסח Pesach is
the oldest. Exactly. And it's not two groups, it's one group. דכי
קתני אחת דמי, D'ki kas achas dami, פסח Pesach all the days
are like in one big group, ופליגי, upligi, and we say it
could mean a middle day. אמרי התם, Amrei hatam, no, no, no,
the reason we say it could be a middle day and this
goes back to say it's not the same debate is not because
any day could be the פני pnei of פסח, Pesach, that's not
the issue. בלישנא דעלמא מפלגי, Blishna d'alma mifligi, they're
discussing what the word פני pnei means. Does the word פני pnei
mean face or does it mean something else? מר סבר עד פני
הפסח עד קמי פסחא, Mar savar ad pnei HaPesach ad kamey Pischa,
פני pnei means like before, you know, לפני, lefanai, before me in
front of me, so therefore it's until the פסח Pesach begins. ומר
סבר עד דמיפני פסחא. U'mar savar ad d'mifnei Pischa. So in Aramaic
מיפני mifnei means to pass, okay, or לפנות lefanot to turn away
or לפנות, lifnot, right, לפנות, lifnot, right, like יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
right,
that's a good point, right, so to pass. So here it's a
simple question of does it mean until פסח Pesach arrives or until
פסח Pesach passes? So it's really not the debate at all that
we were talking about. Okay, good. So we move on. So conceptually
what's at stake is, do people talk or remember in a way
that creates ambiguity? But it was a very, you know, nice read
of אביי Abaye that it's not that the word might mean older,
the word means oldest, but it's, but because there are two groups
it allows for us to question a wider range of people to
whom it refers. Okay, now we go on to the next משנה
Mishna? going back to a issue about who is believed about whether
a marriage took place, and what we're really going to enter into
is a very, very central, it's, you know, it's funny that we
have to wait till sixty-five pages into the מסכת masechet to get
to a core question of a component of the act of קידושין,
Kiddushin? which is, do you need witnesses present not just to validate
that it took place, but actually to constitute the קידושין? Kiddushin That
without witnesses the קידושין Kiddushin halachically is not binding. Okay, that's not
in the משנה, Mishnah it's going to get discussed in the גמרא.
Gemara Let's take a look. האומר לאשה, Ha'omer l'isha, a man says
to a woman, קידשתיך, Kidashitich, I married you, והיא אומרת לא קידשתני,
v'hi omeret lo kidashtani, you did not marry me. Okay. הוא אסור
בקרובותיה
והיא מותרת בקרוביו. Hu assur bikrovoteha v'hi muteret bikrovav. So this gets
back to you can't say something and on your say-so forbid somebody
else, you know, you sort of, you know,
be believed about a, I mean a father can say it about
his children, his underage children, but you cannot say it about another
person, you know, oh, I married you and now this person is
bound by that. So the woman is not bound by his statement,
so she can marry any man and she can even marry like,
for example, like this guy's father or son or brother, from her
perspective we assume she's completely unmarried. From his perspective he's bound by
it. So what does it mean that he's bound by the fact
that he married this woman? It doesn't prevent him from marrying another
woman, but it does prevent him from marrying her mother, her sister,
her daughter, etc. Okay, so he is bound by his statement, she
is not. היא אומרת קידשתני, Hi omeret kidashtani, she says, you married
me, והוא אומר לא קידשתיך, v'hu omer lo kidashtich, I did not
marry you. הוא מותר בקרובותיה, Hu muter bikrovoteha, he can marry her
relatives, והיא אסורה בקרוביו, v'hi asura bikrovav,
but she cannot marry his relatives. The funny thing is not only
can she not marry his relatives, she can't marry any other man.
She's claiming that she's already married to this guy. So, but it
means that either she can't marry any other man or if the
guy agrees and we'll see in the גמרא Gemara, we try to
encourage him to give her a גט, get, okay, even though she
brought it on herself. What? If he doesn't want to? We'll talk
about that. Anyway, but she will still, she will always remain or
even if the guy dies, for example. She's always going to remain
forbidden to his relatives. Okay, but it's funny that it jumps to
relatives. The more immediate thing is she can't marry anyone. All right,
so all right, so the גמרא Gemara. wants to contrast it to
the other case. I understand. Okay. קידשתיך, Kidashtich, he says קידשתיך, Kidashtich,
I married you. והיא אומרת, Vehi omeret, לא קידשת אלא את בתי.
Lo kidasht ela et biti. No, you didn't marry me, you married
my daughter. Okay. So הוא אסור בקרובות גדולה, Hu assur bekrovot gedola,
he cannot marry her relatives, of the, you know, of the mother,
the one he's talking to. The גדולה now she is מותרת בקרוביו.
muteret bekrovav. She doesn't say she's married to him, so she can
marry his relatives. Okay. And הוא מותר בקרובות קטנה, Hu mutar bekrovot
ktana, he's married, he can marry the relatives of the younger one.
I mean sometimes there'll be an overlap of relatives obviously between mother
and daughter, but some won't. Okay. So he can marry the relatives
of the younger one because he never said he was married to
the younger one. והקטנה מותרת בקרוביו, Vehaktana muteret bekrovav, not only that,
the younger one can marry his relatives because the mother's claim that
she was married, this is in contrast to before, before we learned
the father's claim about that he married his daughter binds the daughter,
but the mother's claim that she married off the daughter does not
bind the daughter or that the daughter is married does not bind
the daughter. Okay. So this case nobody is אסור. assur. Okay. He's
claiming he didn't marry anyone, she's claiming you married my daughter, and
so the only claim that exists is hers and she's not believed
about her daughter. What? What about rabbinically? So even rabbinically the גמרא
Gemara is going to say that's the חידוש. chiddush. That the חידוש
chiddush is that we don't say that the same way the father
can do it biblically, the mother can do it rabbinically. No, the
mother is not believed about the marriage status of the daughter. Does
it make a difference what this daughter says? Well, if the daughter's
an adult and she says it then— No, then it wouldn't matter.
No, I know, I agree. No, nope, no status. קידשתי
את בתך. Kidashti et bitech. Now he says, I married your daughter.
והיא אומרת, Vehi omeret, לא קידשת אלא אותי. Lo kidasht ela oti.
No, no, no, you married me. Okay. So now each one of
them is believed based on what they said. הוא אסור בקרובות קטנה,
Hu assur bekrovot ktana, he can't marry the relatives of the daughter
because that's what he said. והקטנה מותרת בקרוביו, Vehaktana muteret bekrovav, the
daughter can marry his relatives because
the daughter didn't say anything about herself. הוא מותר בקרובות גדולה, Hu
mutar bekrovot gedola, he can marry the relatives of the mother because
he never said anything about her. והגדולה אסורה בקרוביו, Vehagedola assura bekrovav,
but she said that she's married to him, so she can't marry
his relatives. Okay. So it's all basically one simple principle which is
you're bound by your statement. And the other point is that a
mother's statement about her daughter is not—does not bind the daughter, is
not believed in terms of the daughter. Okay, let's see the גמרא,
Gemara yeah. But the קטנה ktana would
be—I can't believe that the קטנה ktana would not be believed, she's
never believed to say she's married to anyone? Once she's an adult
she is, not as a minor. Really?
Why not? I mean like— Because testimony of a minor is not
accepted.
So we see her in—so she wouldn't be put to death or
something like that if— Absolutely not, that's even a much higher standard.
No, but I guess like the whole point is you know you
can marry off a קטנה ktana so— Yeah, because we believe the
father. Or the husband, just never the wife. No, we don't believe
the husband. That's his case, we don't believe the husband about vis-à-vis
the—we believe him vis-à-vis himself, not vis-à-vis somebody else. The only thing
that establishes the status of a person for other—you know, not for
the person to bind themselves but for objectively like for the courts
and for other—to be effective for other people would only be either
a father about his underage children or two witnesses. Okay.
So nobody can ever say anything about themselves that affects other people,
right? I can't make a status about me that like say—you know,
the only thing I can do is I can prove—I limit myself
by my own statement. Right, but the קטנה ktana, can't even do
that. Because she's a minor. So it means these two people, let's
say according to the husband, and this wife who's a קטנה, they've
been married for 10 years, from 2 till like 12, they're not
believed at all? There's no other witnesses or anything like that? Well,
that's a different story. That's like how much do you look at
the circumstances that they've been living together as husband and wife or
whatever created a type of a חזקה chazaka and then and so
on, that's a completely different case. You've changed the scenario, that's not
just בפירוש. befirush. Okay. We're dealing here just now with בפירוש. befirush.
All right, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara האומר לאשה
קידשתיך Ha-omer le-isha kidashtich וצריכה. utzricha.
You need to say both cases about, you know, about what he
says and what she says. דאי אשמעינן גבי דידיה, De-i ashmeinan gabei
didey, that he says something, he's only believed vis-à-vis himself but not
to affect her. משום דגברא לא איכפת ליה ומקרי אמר. mishum degavra
lo ikhpat leh umikrei amar. That, you know, for him it costs
very little to say he's married to a woman, right? Because it
only—it really only restricts him from marrying like the mother and the
daughter or whatever. It's not like when a woman says she's married
to a man, that's huge, right? Because now she's basically saying she
can't marry any other man. So for him since it costs him
very little to— Potential כתובה, ketubah, he has to pay—it costs him
quite a lot potentially.
קידושין kiddushin. is not נישואין, nisu'in, so it doesn't actually. If it
was נישואין nisu'in it might be different, it's קידושין. Kiddushin, Anyway, so
it costs like very little. So therefore we'll say of course he
says something we can't bind this other—this woman based on it. You
know, men'll just say that, it doesn't cost them anything. Okay. האומר—אבל
היא, but she, אימא אי לאו דקים לה בדיבוריה, eima i lav
dekim leh bedibureh, if she did not really know what she was
talking about when she said she was married to this guy... Of
course he says something we can't bind this woman based on it.
You know people, men will just say that, it doesn't cost them
anything. Okay. דמפני דגברא לא איכפת ליה ומיקלי אמר, d'mifne d'gavra lo
ikhpat lei u'mikli amar, he'll just say it. אבל היא, Aval hi,
but she, אימא דלא דקימא בדיבורא הכי, eima d'la dakima b'dibbura hachi,
when she did not really know what she was talking about when
she said she was married to this guy. לא הוי אמרה למיסר
נפשה בקרובתיה, lo havi amra l'meisar nafsha b'krovateih,
and she would not have said it, לא הוי אמרה, lo havi
amra, she would not have said it. So meaning when she says
she's married to a guy, she's now saying she's אסור assur to
marry anybody else in the world, right? That's huge. So when you
say somebody's going to do that to themselves, it must be they're
telling the truth, and at least, maybe he doesn't have to pay
her a כתובה, ketubah, but ולמיסר איהו בקרובתה, u'l'meisar ihu b'krovateih, at
least he shouldn't be able, we shouldn't let him marry her relatives.
I mean, at least we should believe what she's saying enough to
not let him go ahead and marry this girl's sister or mother.
קמשמע לן kamashma lan that we don't give it any value, even
though we could make a reasonable argument, but that's really tough. Even
if there's a very powerful reason to believe I'm telling the truth,
how much is that going to be able to make something forbidden
on you? Okay. And that's sort of like we said before when
the guy, you know, says, tries to make, say that she's obligated
in יבום yibbum when we were presuming she wasn't obligated in יבום.
yibbum. So even though, yeah, there's a good reason to think she
might be telling the truth, we're not going to make it forbidden
on the husband. Okay. קידשתיך והיא אומרת לא קידשתני. kiddashtikh v'hi omeret
lo kiddashtani. הא תו למה לי? ha tu lama li? So why
do you need this case of the mother when the mother says
something about the daughter? So איצטריך, itzterikh, you need to tell it
to me. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atakh amina, I would have thought
מדאורייתא הימניה רחמנא לאב, m'deoraita heimneih rachmana l'av, this is what David
was saying, biblically the father believes, the Torah believes the father about
the status of the daughter. מדרבנן הימנוה לדידה, m'derabbanan heimenunah l'didah,
rabbinically let's believe her about her daughter. ותיסר ברתה בדיבורה, v'teisar barta
b'dibbura, and let the daughter be forbidden, at least ברתה, barta, the
daughter, rabbinically. ותיסר ברתה בדיבורה, v'teisar barta b'dibbura, let the daughter be
forbidden by her words. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that no, that she's
not believed at all. Now, קידשתי את בתך, kiddashti et bitekh, etc.
Now, how about this case where like he says I married your
daughter and she says you married me? הא תו למה לי? ha
tu lama li? Why do you need the final case in the
משנה? Mishnah איידי דתנא הא תנא הא. aidi d'tana ha tana ha.
Yeah, the last case you didn't need, but we're just showing because
it's like a parallel of the second to last case. Okay. אתמר
רב אמר כופין. itmar Rav amar kofin. Rav says in the case
well we'll see in a minute but I'll tell you. In the
case where she says you married me and he says I didn't,
Rav says we force him to give a גט. get. ושמואל אמר
מבקשין, u'Shmuel amar mevakshin, we ask him to give a גט. get.
אהיי, a-hei, now on which case are they saying this? אילימא רישא,
ilima reisha, where he says I married you and she says no
you didn't. לא כופי איכא ולא מבקשי איכא. lo kofi ika v'lo
mevakshi ika. There's no need to give a גט. get. She says
you didn't, she's totally free to marry anybody she wants, right? When
he says I married and she says no, why would we ask
for a גט? get? אלא סיפא, ela seifa, the end, where she
says you married me and now she is bound and she can't
marry any other man. So בשלמא מבקשין, bishlama mevakshin, I guess why
you would say to say look, do a favor, write her a
גט. get. She's now said this thing, she's bound, she can't marry
anybody else. Write her a גט. get. לחי, le-chai, that makes sense.
אלא כופין אמאי? ela kofin amai? Why would you force the guy
to write a גט? get? Like he's saying now why not, like
maybe like just out of רחמנות rachmanut for this woman? Because if
he writes a גט, get, he's going to be acknowledging that he's,
he was married to her and now he's divorced her and now
he can't marry the relatives. So it actually does, you know, does
limit him. But he'd have to pay for all incidentals, right? Presumably.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says how could you force?
אמר לא ניחא לי דאיסר בקרובי. amar lo nicha li d'eisar b'krovei.
I don't want to write a גט, get, that'll make it that
she's my divorcee and then I won't be able to marry any
relative, her relatives. So the גמרא gemara says, yeah, that's right. אלא
שמעתתא אהדדי איתמרו. ela shmattata ahadadi itmaru. You're right. This isn't a
debate, they're actually adding on what one another said. Okay. When I
once took an improv course they teach you the first rule of
the improv is you don't say no but, you say yes and.
Like so, so like a rule for life. Like if somebody starts
a story you don't try to contradict and start a different story.
It's yes and, and then build on their story. Anyway, so that's
what they're saying. They're not saying no but, they're saying yes and.
אמר שמואל מבקשין ממנו ליתן גט. amar Shmuel mevakshin mimenu litten get.
When she says that she's married to him, Shmuel says you request
the guy, do a favor, write her a גט. get. אמר רב,
amar Rav, and Rav says ואם נתן גט מעצמו, v'im natan get
mei-atzmo, now if he gave a גט get on his own initiative,
not because we pushed him to give a גט, get, he just
on his own gave a גט, get, then כופין אותו ליתן כתובה.
kofin oto litten ketubah. We see that as an admission that he
was married to her and now he's forced to give a כתובה.
ketubah. So like you, so if you're a good guy, the basic
point is wait till בית דין... Beit Din... no, wait till the
בית דין Beit Din says, you know, you should really do the
right thing and write a גט get and then you could write
it and it'll be clear that it's not an admission. Okay, so
it makes it clear for the record like I'm just doing this
because I know you guys feel into this trouble here. Right. I
don't know, I don't know exactly what the line is between מעצמו
mei-atzmo and מבקשין. mevakshin. But don't, but it's really, sometimes that's a
lesson. Don't be too good of a guy, okay? It'll get you
in trouble. All right. What? Now, איתמר נמי הכי. itmar nami hachi.
It was also taught, אמר רב אחא בר אדא אמר רב. amar
Rav Acha bar Adda amar Rav. ואמרי לה אמר רב אחא בר
אדא אמר רב המנונא אמר רב. v'amrei lah amar Rav Acha bar
Adda amar Rav Hamnuna amar Rav. כופין ומבקשין. kofin u'mevakshin. You force
and you ask. תרתי? tartei? Which one is it? Do you force
or do you ask? So הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. מבקשין ממנו ליתן
גט. mevakshin mimenu litten get. You ask him to give a גט.
get. ואם נתן מעצמו, v'im natan mei-atzmo, but if he gives on
his own initiative, then כופין אותו ליתן כתובה. kofin oto litten ketubah.
Then it's an admission and you force him to give a כתובה.
ketubah. Okay. What? Can she just concede, can she formally forgo the
receiving of the כתובה? ketubah? Yeah.
So I mean that's true too. I mean that would be a
way about מבקשין, mevakshin, you know, but from, but the point would
be if he's only responding to a בית דין's Beit Din's מבקשין
mevakshin she doesn't even have to forgo it. We don't
look at it
as... Now we turn to what might be like one of the
biggest סוגיות, sugyot, important סוגיות sugyot in contemporary הלכות קידושין, Hilchos Kiddushin,
you know, which we had to wait 64 דפין dappin to get
to, okay, which is the need for kosher witnesses to make it
a binding קידושין, Kiddushin because a lot of the ways in which
עגונה agunah issues are dealt with nowadays is to say, well, there
weren't really any kosher witnesses there and so on, etc. So let's
take a look.
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, המקדש בעד אחד אין חוששין לקידושיו.
hamikadesh be'ed echad ein chosheshin lekiddushav. If somebody marries a woman and
there is only one witness present, the marriage is not binding; without
two witnesses the marriage is not binding. Now, בעו מיניה מרב יהודה,
ba'u minei miRav Yehuda, they asked Rav Yehuda, שניהם מודים מאי? shneihem
modim mai? Now, when you say one witness doesn't mean anything, do
you mean what I just said, which is that
even if it 100% occurred, it's not binding without the presence of
two witnesses?
Or do you mean one witness is not enough to prove that
it occurred? What would be a test case? Let's say everybody agrees.
The man agrees, the woman agrees, one witness says it. So as
far as we're concerned, we have no doubt that it took place,
but there were not two witnesses present. So is that is it
a question of proving it or is it a question about whether
it's necessary to make it legally binding? So and the case is
if they both agree and a witness says it, we presume that
it definitely took place, is it still is it not binding in
that case? קידושין Kiddushin, again, right, not נישואין? nissuim? קידושין, Kiddushin, because
we heard the yeah, yeah, yeah, קידושין, Kiddushin. just the act of
קידושין. Kiddushin So ולא פשטה בידיה, v'lo pashat b'yadei, so he'd say
yes, no, it was weak in his hand, which basically means he
would vacillate, he didn't know the answer to that, right? He didn't
know whether the need for two witnesses is to prove that it
occurred or to make it occur, to to is it constitutive? Okay,
so the גמרא gemara says איתמר, itmar, now it was
stated, אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, המקדש
בעד אחד אין חוששין לקידושיו. hamikadesh be'ed echad ein chosheshin lekiddushav. So
now it's a statement in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, with one
witness it's not good, ואפילו שניהם מודים, va'afilu shneihem modim,
even if they both agree, explicit. It doesn't matter, 100% we knew
it occurred, if there were not two witnesses it's not binding. You
could have had the video, okay, it doesn't matter, without two witnesses
it's not binding. So who were the two ones? The husband and
the wife? Alright. איתיביה oseivei רבא Rava לרב נחמן, leRav Nachman, now
רבא Rava asked רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, supposed or alleged husband? Right,
exactly. האומר לאשה קידשתיך. ha'omer l'ishah kidashtich. Now let's go to our
משנה Mishnah. because our משנה Mishnah was he said she said type
of a thing and it seems like you didn't need any witnesses
in our
משנה. האומר לאשה קידשתיך והיא אומרת לא קידשתני הוא אסור בקרובותיה והיא
מותרת בקרוביו. ha'omer l'ishah kidashtich vehi omeret lo kidashtani hu assur bikrovoteha
vehi muteret bikrovav. אי דאיכא עדים, ei d'ika eidim, so אמאי מותרת
בקרוביו? amai muteret bikrovav? If there are witnesses, how is anybody מותר,
mutter, how is she מותרת mutteres in his relatives? The witnesses say
they're married. ואי דליכא עדים, v'ei d'leika eidim, and if there are
no witnesses, אמאי אסור בקרובותיה? amai assur bikrovoteha? Why is he bound?
There's no witnesses, right? It sounds like you don't need witnesses. אלא
לאו בעד אחד? ela lav be'ed echad? It must be there's one
witness. And if
there's one witness and שניהם מודים, shneihem modim, then we say they're
definitely married. If there's one witness and one of them says they're
married, then that guy is considered to be married. Okay, so you
it's the combination of the witness and the claims of the people.
No, wait, wait, but time out, don't we have a concept also
like שויא אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא? shavyei anafshei chaticha d'issura? But not if
you said you did an act that doesn't bind you, right? If
I said I did an act of קידושין Kiddushin which I didn't
mean it, I'm saying I gave this woman a ring which was
less than a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. Would we say oh now
you're considered married to her? No. So if you say I married
this woman and there weren't witnesses present, so you didn't do anything
meaningful. Okay, so so base so it must be you don't need
witnesses to be present in order for the קידושין kiddushin to be
binding. You have a witness that supports your statement and you're saying
it and now at least it's אסור assur for you. So in
the משנה also that you know we were talking about the sort
of witness המקדש בתו, hamikadesh bito, as there is or. Yeah, that
he would have to claim that there was, right, so right, that
those one that if either one or two witnesses. Yeah, I mean
we'll get to that. So let's just see the answer, okay? So
doesn't it so it must be you don't need two witnesses or
else it wouldn't be an objective issue and it must be one
witness suffices with somebody's admission. And here one side admits and that's
the combination of a witness and one admission. So
the גמרא gemara says לא הכא במאי עסקינן, lo hacha bemai askinan,
what are we talking about?
כגון דאמר לה קידשתיך בפני פלוני ופלוני והלכו להם למדינת הים. kegon
de'amar lah kidashtich bifnei ploni uploni vehalchu lahem limdinat hayam. No, what
we're talking about is he says there were witnesses. It's like he
says I married you, the ring was a שוה פרוטה, shaveh perutah,
I married you there were witnesses. They're not here, but I'm still
saying that I did it הלכתית halachikly correct. And just because there
were witnesses at that time doesn't mean that they're testifying. So going
back to Michael's question, to say no, you didn't marry me and
there were no witnesses. Well if you didn't marry me there were
no witnesses, okay, or she could be saying yeah you gave me
the ring but there weren't witnesses present. She could be saying anything,
anything that denies that it was a binding act. Or the witnesses
were פסול. pasul. Right, or whatever, yeah. Now all which means all
the previous cases of claims, like when the father says I married
off my daughter, right, all those cases is in the presence of
witnesses. And all those cases about questions about is he telling the
truth or not or whatever has to be that he's claiming there
were witnesses. and we don't have access to those witnesses or he
didn't tell us who those witnesses were. But now you understand the
simple sense of all these משניות mishnayos presume that you don't need
witnesses. And we have completely now revolutionized, I mean we know for
הלכה halakha that it's central, but the this is like a huge
חידוש chiddush to read into all these משניות mishnayos that are discussing
who do you believe that it's always with a claim that witnesses
were present even though they're not being produced right now. Alright let's
take a look just get to the bottom of the page. So
the גמרא says like this: איתיבי, Aitivi, I'll ask you on
this: המגרש Hamagaresh אשתו ishto ולנה velana עמו immo בפונדקי, bepundaki, a
man divorced his wife and you know a year later they happen
to meet up and were traveling together and they spent the night
together in an inn. Okay, so are we afraid that because they
already have a previous relationship to build off of that they would
have slept together and that would implicitly be קידושי kiddushay ביאה. biah.
Now they're remarried. So בית Beis שמאי Shammai אומרים omrim אינה aina
צריכה tzericha הימנו mimenu גט get שני, sheini, no we're not concerned
with that. You don't need another
גט. get. ובית U'Beis הלל Hillel אומרים omrim צריכה tzericha הימנו mimenu
גט get שני, sheini, you need to give another גט. get. היכי
Heichi דמי, dami, what's the case? אי Ei דאיכא de-ika עדים, aidim,
if there are witnesses that saw them having sex, מאי mai טעמא
taama דבית de-Beis שמאי? Shammai? What's Beis Shammai's reasoning to not require
a גט? get? אי דליכא de-leka עדים, aidim, and if there were
no witnesses, מאי mai טעמא taama דבית de-Beis הלל, Hillel, why would
Beis Hillel say they need a גט? get? אלא Ella לאו, lav,
it must be בעד be-aid אחד, echad, there was one witness and
then the question would be like somehow, you know, one witness would
be
sufficient so Beis Shammai could say maybe we don't give weight to
that one witness and Beis Hillel says we do and maybe that's
what their debate is about. Anyway, it's a funny הוה havah אמינא
aminah because the גמרא is going to say there's a much easier
way to explain what they're debating. For the תאימיך, tameich, the גמרא
says according to you, אימא סיפא, seifa, let's look at the end
of that.
ומודים U'modim בנתגרשה benitgarsha מן min האירוסין, ha-eirusin, they would agree that
if they had never actually had sex together, they had a קידושין
kiddushin and then they were divorced and they never consummated their marriage,
in that case שאינה she-aina צריכה tzericha הימנו mimenu גט get שני.
sheini. You don't need a second גט get because they never, you
don't assume that just because they were in the same inn together
that they slept together. So clearly if that's the issue, you see
what the question is, is not whether there were enough witnesses, not
enough witnesses. The question is what do we presume happened in the
inn? So if they were never had you know had sex in
the past, we don't presume that they've had sex now. But if
they have had sex in the past and they were married before
in the past, that's where Beis Hillel and Beis Shammai disagree: what
do we assume happened right now? So it's a question about what
do we guess might have happened and not whether קידושין kiddushin. needs
witnesses or doesn't need witnesses. Okay and so let's just finish this.
שאין She-ein לבו libo גס gass בה bah that he's not too
comfortable with her in that case, you know, won't it self so.
ואי סלקא salka דעתך daatach עד aid אחד echad נאמן, ne'eman, and
if it's really a one witness is testifying, מה mah לי li
מן min האירוסין ha-eirusin מה mah לי li מן min הנישואין? ha-nisuin?
If witnesses saw what happened, then it doesn't matter what the previous
history is between the two of them. אלא, Ella, here's what's going
on, and this is clear that this was always the case.
Okay, הכא hacha במאי be-mai עסקינן askinan כגון kegon דאיכא עידי aidei
ייחוד, yichud, witnesses saw them go into the inn together. וליכא Ve-leka
עידי aidei ביאה, biah, nobody saw if they had sex.
בית Beis שמאי Shammai סברי savri לא lo אמרינן amrinan הן hein
הן hein עידי aidei ייחוד yichud הן hein הן hein עידי aidei
ביאה. biah. Beis Shammai says we don't presume that just because they
were in seclusion we should presume that that's considered like there's testimony
that they had sex and that makes them considered now married, meaning
now you could read that two ways: maybe we don't presume they
had sex but it's not halakhically defined as testimony that they had
sex, right? It's not considered direct evidence that they had sex. So
therefore they're not married.
ובית U'Beis הלל Hillel סברי savri אמרינן amrinan הן hein הן hein
עידי aidei ייחוד yichud הן hein הן hein עידי aidei ביאה. biah.
If they've already been married before and have had sex before, we're
going to say, and witnesses saw them into go into seclusion, then
that's like the witnesses saw them have sex, and therefore that constitutes
a new act of
קידושין. kiddushin One minute, ומודים u'modim ודאי vaday בנתגרשה benitgarsha מן min
האירוסין, ha-eirusin, but if they had never had sex before, then they
agree דלא de-lo אמרינן amrinan הן hein הן hein עידי aidei ייחוד
yichud הן hein הן hein עידי aidei ביאה biah מפני mipnei שאין
she-ein לבו libo גס gass בה. bah. We do not say that
seeing them go into seclusion is like testifying to sex because then
they did not have that past history and we cannot presume that.
So basically this has nothing to do, we could totally assume that
קידושין kiddushin requires witnesses and the question now becomes a separate question:
what do the witnesses have to see? So the debate of Beis
Hillel and Beis Shammai is, is it like the witnesses saw them
having sex or not? How much do we presume happened and how
much can we translate that into what we say it's as if
the witnesses saw. Okay, so we'll continue though tomorrow in this central
question about whether קידושין kiddushin, requires witnesses to actually make it a
binding קידושין, and if it does then the question sometimes as we've
seen what constitutes that they've actually seen the act or not, and
that's what's going on here with Beis Hillel and Beis Shammai.